Regarding parental and relative objections to my leaving home, I'm seeking guidance on the auspicious path of reciting
tư vấn đề bố mẹ người thân cản trở xuất
Buddha's name,
ra mẹ con thuận duyên Niệm Phật có
vowing to be reborn in the Pure Land, and frequently listening to
nguyện vãng sinh tịnh độ và thường nghe
lectures on the Pure Land Dharma. I've
các bài giảng về Pháp Môn Tịnh Độ Con đã
told my parents about my aspirations, and
nói với bố mẹ về chí nguyện của mình ban
initially, they disagreed, but now my mother is
đầu bố mẹ không đồng ý nhưng giờ mẹ đã
gradually agreeing. My father doesn't openly object, but he often
dần đồng ý Còn bố tôi không phản đối
criticizes my mother for reciting
trước mặt nhưng hay nói và trách mẹ hay
Buddha's name and listening to Dharma teachings, thinking I'm being
niệm phật và nghe pháp nên nghĩ con bị
influenced. He even doesn't want my mother to listen to Dharma teachings
ảnh hưởng bố còn không muốn mẹ nghe pháp
or recite Buddha's name when I'm home. This has caused
hay niệm phật khi con về nhà việc này là
my mother a lot of worry. My mother said that if my
mẹ con suy nghĩ rất nhiều Mẹ bảo nếu con
father continues to be so troublesome, she'll have to repay his kindness.
đi bố cứ phiền nỏ như vậy thì phải báo
She recently agreed to let me go to the
hiếu không vừa rồi mẹ đồng ý cho con về
temple to practice, but she also wants me to join a
chùa tu tập nhưng mẹ cũng muốn con vào
Buddhist love, marriage, and family club,
Phật tử
hoping I won't be too attached to the idea of
ý muốn tâm con đừng quá chấp là mình
constantly being away. I agreed to let her. Am I
phải đi suốt ra con đã Vâng để mẹ đồng ý
lying to her? My
như vậy có phải đang nói dối mẹ không ạ
mother says that going to the temple requires sufficient material resources
Mẹ con nói về chùa phải có vật chất đủ
for living expenses during my time there.
để mình sinh hoạt trong khoảng thời gian
She fears I won't be able to practice properly and that
ở chùa Mẹ sợ con tu tao không A và còn
my merit will decrease. I feel weak in many
giảm Phước con thấy mình non yếu nhiều
aspects of my knowledge and practice, so I'm
mặt tri kiến tu tập thì hỏi nên con chần
hesitant and unsure whether I should work and study
chừ phân vân hay là vừa làm vừa tu học
at a center to improve myself.  I'm afraid that if I give it to her,
tại khối để trau dồi nhưng sợ khi đó cho
she'll only want more,
rồi con lại càng muốn có nhiều hơn muốn
fame, connections, and
danh vọng rồi nhân duyên hướng và ái dục
sensual desires. I beg you, please give me some
con xin cô cho con lời khuyên
advice, especially if I'm lying to my mother.
ý tư nhất là con có phải đang nói dối mẹ
In Buddhism, there's a part about
không thì ở trong Phật pháp có cái phần
skillful means. When someone
nói nói phương tiện khi kinh người mà
doesn't understand the scriptures, we can't explain everything.
chưa hiểu thì ta không thể nói hết được
For example, the Buddha also spoke of skillful
ví dụ như Đức Phật cũng có thể nói
means. Besides, that old man, 90
phương tiện Với lại cái ông lão mà có 90
years old, keeps asking to go to the intermediate
tuổi ông xin đòi đi suốt ra đấy trung
level of Arhatship, but to enter, you have to observe
cấp bậc a-la-hán mà vào là phải hành trì
250 precepts, this way, that way, that way. He's
250 giới thì thế này thế này thế kia ông
afraid of giving up and doesn't say it's only for the 250 precepts.
sợ bỏ và không bảo dành cho mảng chỉ 250
Now, how can it be easy to read all that? Even after reading it all, I still
rơi giờ dễ nào dưới lòng đọc hết cả mắt
see the Buddha only saying that you
rồi thấy Đức Phật ra vẫn còn chỉ nói là
only need to give up greed, anger, and delusion—those three things.
chỉ cần bỏ Tham Sân Si có ba việc ấy
Love your wife, and if you can do that, then you can enter. Then you
thôi thương vợ thì con làm được thì vào
start teaching gradually, little by little,
rồi thì bắt đầu mới dậy dần thì à một
not all at once
chút từng chút một chứ không cá hết tất
like the
cả một khối giống như là các bậc
Arhats above the Buddha. And the Arhats are
a-la-hán trên Đức Phật Và bậc a-la-hán
all the greatest in the same school; there's no
với nhau cùng lớn nhất môn cả không có
two sayings, right? It's not that I don't give, but the way of
hai lời phải không cho nhưng mà cái cách
saying it is different, so the reception is different.
nói khác nhau để tiếp nhận khác nhau
Where are we going? My wife is like that, the flower is in
giữa đâu mà Còn vợ thế thôi bông ở trong
the shrimp, my parents don't understand that, that's
cái tôm là bố mẹ chưa hiểu điều đó thế
all, it's not like we're chickens. We
thôi chứ không phải là gà Chúng ta là
agree, we go in there, or
đồng ý chúng ta đi vào đó hay là chúng
we deceive our parents, there's some
ta lừa dối cha mẹ chúng ta một con vấn
issue that my parents don't understand, so it's better to
đề gì đó mà cha mẹ chưa hiểu thì hơn cấp
put them in a club first, then from one
cho vào câu lạc bộ đã rồi sẽ từ câu lạc
club to another, from the
bộ lọ chuyển nó câu lạc bộ kia từ câu
love and marriage club to the
lạc bộ tình yêu hôn nhân Đến câu lạc bộ
liberation club, gradually going through each club
giải thoát nó đi dần dần từng câu lạc bộ
one by one, just consider the club as enough. As for going to the
một cứ coi trícâu lạc bộ là được
temple, if you're materialistic,
cái còn nói là về chùa phải con vật chất
then you're not going to the temple. If you're
thì không phải về chùa Trả thù con vật
materialistic, then we all have the aspiration to stay at the
chất thì cả chúng ta cứ có tâm nguyện ở
temple, even if we have to sweep the temple, we have more than enough strength to do so,
chùa dù có đi quét chùa cũng thừa sức
no need to worry. I'm not talking about that
can không phải lo gì Không nói cái vấn
issue. Currently, I'm studying
đề đó Hiện tại cháu đang đi học đại học
pharmacy at university, graduating in July 2020.
khoa dược tháng 7 năm 20 A6 ra trường
After listening to the video of the master lecturing on the
sau khi nghe video sư phụ Giảng về ý
meaning of studying at university, I
nghĩa của học tập ở trường đại học cho
think that I study to gain knowledge.
cô suy nghĩ là mình học để có kiến thức
Even if I may not apply it later, I
Dù sau này có thể không áp dụng nhưng
still have the mindset. Once again, I'm going to school
vẫn có tư duy một lần nữa là cháu đi học
so my mother won't be sad anymore. My father passed away in
để mẹ cháu đỡ buồn non nắng bố cháu mất
2019.  I only have my mother and
năm 2019 nhà cháu chỉ còn mẹ và hai chị
my two sisters left. I'm constantly thinking about going
em cháu Cháu vẫn thường trực suy nghĩ
to the temple after finishing my studies. But in my heart, I wonder
học xong về chùa luôn Nhưng trong tâm
what I'll do if the pandemic prevents me from going to the temple. I feel I'm
được thì mình làm gì cháu thấy bản thân
not enlightened enough, not strong enough to abandon
chưa đủ giác ngộ Chưa mạnh mẽ mà bỏ tất
everything to go to the temple. I don't really want to
cả để về chùa cháu không thật sự muốn
work in the world, but I'm afraid I won't be able to go to the
làm việc ở đời nhưng lại sợ không về
temple because of the pandemic. My family is against it, and I have
chùa được do dịch gia đình cản cháu cũng
n't been able to encourage my mother to practice according to the
chưa Khuyến tấn được mẹ tu tập theo chúa
Golden Buddha teachings. I ask you, teacher, to guide me.
vàng Cháu xin cô chỉ dậy
Of course, I'll just do a little bit of writing.
dịch thì đương nhiên là chỉ đi tép tép
You've already written it, at most it'll be about how to record it in
cô viết rồi cùng lắm là về cách ghi lúc
15-21 days, that's all. The
15 21 ngày là xong có gì đâu trên cái
pandemic isn't something to
việc dịch thì không đáng lo nhá Thế còn
worry about. But how can we ensure my mother can pass away peacefully? Let's dedicate our merits from now on. In the process of living, let's be obedient, let's open up those things and practice filial piety. Where does that come from? That's filial piety. That's how my mother feels the least. From
thấy cảm ít dân cảm nhất dân đó nhé từ
those Dharma practices that we can
những cái váy pháp mà mình có thể thực
practice for our parents to experience, and
hành để cho bố mẹ trải nghiệm và phật
Buddhist teachings don't just open up discussions about filial piety,
pháp thì không mở những bàn về Hữu Thuận
abandoning evil and doing good. Those are just
bỏ ác làm lành những cái bài đấy súng
good teachings.  So, how does it work? My parents see
thiện là đây thế nào bố mẹ mình thấy
me and this Dharma teaching as one? If
mình với cái bài pháp này là một quả
my parents see me and this
đấy bố mẹ mình thấy mình với cái bài
Dharma teaching as one, they will appreciate the
pháp là một thì bố mẹ mình sẽ cảm mến
Dharma and gradually listen to it more and more.
pháp và dần dần cứ nghe Dần nghe dần lên
Maybe they will understand it before me. Then,
Có khi bố mẹ lại thấm trước Minh mày
depending on the circumstances, I will gradually explain. (
không Rồi mình tùy duyên mình nói dần
491) Actually, if I tell
câu 491 Thực Cô nếu cháu nói ý định xuất
someone who doesn't have faith in Buddhism that I intend to leave this world,
ra với người chưa có tín tâm với Phật
they will say, "You have a
Pháp họ sẽ nói cháu
bad mindset, so will you
anh với tâm lý không tốt thì cháu có bị
be hindered by karma?" What's the
nhân quả sẽ bị cản trở suốt ra không
point of talking to them if
Ý mình nói chuyện với họ làm gì nếu
there's no karmic connection? I wouldn't say
không có nhân duyên thì mình chả nói họ
anything to them. Firstly, if they are not
làm gì cả thứ nhất là họ không có liên
related to me, there's no need to
quan đến mình thì không cần thiết phải
say anything.
nói nhá
Secondly, if my relatives, while alive, were
vị trí 2 Nếu người thân khi còn sống con
unhappy and troubled because of me, they should
không hoan hỷ và phiền não vì mình nên
practice at the temple. When I leave this world, will they
chùa tu tập thì khi bỏ hóa thân có gì
fall into depravity? And how can I
vậy mà bị sa đọa không ạ và làm thế nào
make them understand that my actions are
để họ hiểu những việc mình là
meant to be filial piety? Of course, they and I are
mong muốn báo hiếu ạ và đương nhiên là
both suffering because of my karmic actions.
họ cả mình sốt ra thì trong cái nhân
Their karmic consequences are already present, not just
nghiệp của họ đã có sẵn không sẵn cá
personal karma. When I leave this world,
nhân cả mấy rồi em hết khi mình xuất ra
I will have the opportunity to help them
thì mình lại còn có duyên Giúp cho họ
benefit.  Benefits in the afterlife. For example, on
được lợi ích trong đời sau Ví dụ như là
the day of the Nine Lotuses, wasn't it because the mother, who had a
ngày Cửu Liên có phải là mẹ mãi gái có
pure heart, didn't offer any treasures? It must have been
tâm sẵn là không đưa tam bảo gì chị phải
because of that heart that
do cái tâm đấy chứ nên là bài mới tạo ra
karma was created, and when the time came, the path was cut short. But
nghiệp và đến lúc quá mi bị đoạn nhưng
because of this, a Nine Lotuses appeared and she
do này một Kiều Liên xuất ra trên bà
was saved, right? So, if
được cứu phải không Hãy cho nên mà con
your child is the one you love most,
mình đi suốt ra mình yêu quý nhất thì
even if you create karma, you still have
mình dù có tạo nghiệp thì mình vẫn có
great benefits. For example, the next day, you'll prosper. That
lớn ví dụ như là ngày sau lại phát Đấy
day you saved your mother, that day you went right away, even if you felt
ngày cứu được mẹ ngày đấy đấy đi ngay có
sorrow, your mother had a karmic connection.
đi xót xa thì mẹ ngàn có nhân duyên đó
In the cycle of cause and effect, karma between
nha trong cái trùm nhân quả nghiệp giữa
you and your family is one. There are countless
mình với gia đình mình là một Có chùm
karmic connections. So when you do
chùm nhân quả Thế thì khi mình làm việc
good deeds, at first people may
tốt lên thì mới đầu là người ta còn còn
change, but no one can go
thay đổi nhưng mà không ai có thể làm
against karma, so everything will be
trái nhân quả được cho nên tất ứng có
alright. The Buddha taught us this, and that
phải tốt trên Đức Phật nó dậy mình như
's enough proof.
thế minh chứng là đủ Anh
Now, in Vietnam, Emperor Tran
anh giờ ở Việt Nam là Phật Hoàng Trần
Nhan Tong is a testament to this. So in
Nhân Tông Nam minh chứng cho nên trong
that cycle of karma, when you do good, at
cái dòng + nghiệp đấy mình làm cái tốt
first people may not adapt,
mới đầu mọi người chưa thích ứng được
but later it will be good. For example,
nhưng sau rồi nó sẽ tốt đẹp thôi ví dụ
durian is
những sầu riêng
nutritious and has a special taste.  What I like most is that after
chất bổ với đặc hơi chưa thích đến nhất
eating a few times, I naturally felt stiff, and my
ở mồm ăn vài lần tự nhiên thấy cứng với
body accepted being a flower, covering
cơ thể đã chấp nhận làm hoa cái mũi che
your nose with a mask. Nothing at all,
cho bạn mũi chưa Cái gì cả đều không
Nghia is just kidding, don't worry. Let's see,
thằng Nghĩa nó nhá trên yên tâm nha xem
we just need to get past the first hurdle, then it's over.
chúng ta chỉ cần vượt qua ngưỡng cửa đầu
Everything is better when you see your child is
thôi xong rồi Mọi cái là thấy con mình
safe and well. That's more fun, isn't it? It's better than
bình an tốt mà Vậy vui hơn chứ còn hơn
him staying home and occasionally running off somewhere. He went out
là nó ở nhà thỉnh thoảng nó chạy đi đâu
tonight and didn't come home, I couldn't sleep all
thế Đi chơi đêm nay không về mất ngủ cả
night. Now, suddenly, I don't have to worry about anything all day. I don't have to worry about him, I don't have to worry about
đêm bây giờ tự nhiên thấy cả ngày chả
him, I don't have to worry about his gambling, and I don't have to
phải lo gì nó không phải lo nó cờ và
worry about doing business like this or that. I
không phải lo đó làm ăn có thế này kia
suddenly feel healthier, I don't have to say anything.
không tự nhiên là khỏe ra không nói gì à
[Applause] Yes,
[Vỗ tay]